<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of nobilitie· Preached at VVhite-hall, before the King in February 1606. By George Meriton Doctor of Diuinity, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinary; and parson of Hadleigh in Suffolke.</title>
            <author>Meriton, George, d. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07451</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17838</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112666</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847912</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847912</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12979</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07451)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12979)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1247:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of nobilitie· Preached at VVhite-hall, before the King in February 1606. By George Meriton Doctor of Diuinity, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinary; and parson of Hadleigh in Suffolke.</title>
                  <author>Meriton, George, d. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By George Eld] for Thomas Clarke, and are to be sold at the signe of the Angell in Saint Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12979:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12979:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12979:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12979:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF NOBILITIE. Preached at White-hall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>fore the King in February</hi> 1606.</p>
            <p>By GEORGE MERITON Doctor of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, one of his Maieſties Chaplaines in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>dinary; and Parſon of Hadleigh</hi> in Suffolke.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael: Them that honour mee, I will honour: but they which diſpiſe mee, ſhall bee deſpiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>1. Sam. 2. 30.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Thomas Clarke,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Angell in Saint <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12979:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12979:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Noble <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of Suffolke, Barron of Walden, Lord Chamberlaine to his Maieſty: One of the moſt Honourable Priuy-Counſell, and Knight of the <hi>Noble Order of the Garter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c, increaſe of true honour and euerlasting</hi> happineſſe,</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble Earle,</hi> vouchſafe I beſeech you, to accept of that <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> which was not long ſince <hi>Preached.</hi> It is a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of Nobility:</hi> and vnto none may it more iuſtly bee offered, then vnto your ſelfe: whome <hi>Nature, Vertue, King,</hi> and
<hi>God,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12979:4"/> adornes with eminent Honours. It is alſo a ſmall teſtimony, of my vnfayned duty: who am the Son of him, that was once your L: poore Tenant: borne vnder the roofe of your Honors houſe: and in my youth eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming my ſelfe, as one of yours, Firſt affections makes deepe impresſions: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall euer remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors to be commanded. <hi>GEORGE MERITON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12979:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders all Chriſtian Graces.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble or Gentle Readers. I haue here publiſhed a ſhort Sermon of Nobility. <hi>It is publiſhed:</hi> and perhaps I was drawne herevnto by ſome authority; or elſe prouoked by much intreaty, if by neyther of theſe: yet know, that it is now a faſhion, to preach, and then to print. And though I bee but <hi>merum rus,</hi> a Countrey Miniſter, I would not bee thought to bee worne out of faſhion. <hi>It is a ſhort Sermon.</hi> For it was preachea, not at the
<hi>Croſſe,</hi> but at the <hi>Court:</hi> The one place requiring length, the other expecting breuity. <hi>It is a Sermon of Nobility.</hi> Before Nobles, of a noble Argument<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wordes of good worth, if vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably vttered, ſuſtaine that reproch which <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> receiued from the Prieſts and Rulers in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>quid haec ad nos,</hi> what are theſe to vs? but that which is fitly ſpoken in his time, and place, is, ſaith the Wiſe-man, <hi>Like Apples of Gold, and pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Siluer.</hi> Prouerb. 25. 11. Pretious in it ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:12979:5"/> yet as Iohn ſayd of CHRIST, Iohn the firſt Chapter, and 15. verſe, <hi>He that commeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me, is preferred before me,</hi> ſo muſt wee thinke of theſe two, (how ſocuer the account of the world be otherwiſe) that the <hi>latter</hi> is farre the
<hi>better.</hi> Martha did <hi>well,</hi> in making prouiſion for the foode of the
<hi>body:</hi> but Mary did much <hi>better,</hi> who receiued from Chriſts mouth the foode of her <hi>ſoule:</hi> The <hi>one,</hi> it is but the ſtaffe of <hi>life mortall:</hi> Leuit. the
26. the <hi>other,</hi> the <hi>ſeed of immortalisty,</hi> the firſt of Peter and the firſt Chapter, and <hi>powerfull to ſaluation, vnto all belecuers,</hi> Rom. the 1. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and 16. verſe. From the <hi>former,</hi> vpon a <hi>fullneſſe,</hi> we ought to forbeare: <hi>for the full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of bread, was a ſinne of Sodom,</hi> Ezek. the 16. Chapter: but of the
<hi>latter,</hi> there is neuer ynough; <hi>thy belly ſhall eate it,</hi> ſayeth GOD, <hi>and thy bowels ſhall be filled with it,</hi> Ezek. the third Chapter, and third verſe. In this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I meete with two ſorts of men: The firſt are certaine troubleſome Iewes of
<hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica,</hi> which (like worldly men) ſauour <hi>bread,</hi> the things of this world, more then the things of GOD. The ſecond, are a company of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable men of
<hi>Berea,</hi> more honorable then thoſe of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> who iudge rightly of
<pb facs="tcp:12979:5"/> the <hi>word</hi> of GOD, and ſhew their loue vnto it, by a ready receiuing, and dayly ſearching. The meeting of theſe noble Gentlemen is profitable vnto vs, yeelding by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and practiſe a threefold inſtruction. Firſt, that there are Nobles: (<hi>Theſe were noble men.</hi>) Secondly, that there are diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, or degrees, of nobility. (<hi>Theſe were more noble men then thoſe of Theſſalonica.</hi>) Thirdly, that they haue, and are knowne by their fruites, (<hi>They receiued the word readily, they ſearched it dayly, &amp;c.</hi>) A Treatiſe of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> (if I erre not in conceipt) will not be vnprofitable to ſuch as are <hi>yong Nobles,</hi> who may hereby be more ſtirred vp to propagate and inlarge the ſame: will not be diſtaſtfull <hi>to old Nobles,</hi> who ſeeing the ſeed, and true forme of Nobility ſhining in themſelues, may behold with a glad heart the fruit of it in their poſterity: neither will it be vnfitting <hi>ingenuous men:</hi> for Nobility, and the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all ſuch kind of perſons are by a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py knot conioyned together. Heare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with patience moſt honorable, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous, <hi>&amp; Deus faxit argumentum hoc, tam ſit commodum, quam eſt accommodum,</hi> and GOD make this argument as profitable vnto
<pb facs="tcp:12979:6"/> you, as it is fit and ſutable for you.</p>
            <p>There be Nobles. <hi>Theſe were Noble men.</hi> Stoicks the old brokers of parity, and their ſucceſſors the Engliſh Switzers of theſe our dayes, ſuppoſing <hi>Nobility</hi> to be but a meere fiction, or deuice of men in higher place, haue made a fooliſh doubt, whether there be ſuch a thing in the world or no? Let vs indure awhile to heare them to ſpeake:
<hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (<hi>ſay they</hi>) <hi>is an equal parent vnto all, a ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother vnto none: God made but one Adam, not one of ſiluer to be the father of Nobles, and another of earth to beget the common ſort: none are barred of their way to vertue, or hindered of their courſe to true felicity. Not</hi> Scythia, <hi>or any other region vnder heauen doth hurt the minde, neither is one kindred to be accounted more auncient then another: God tooke his firſt King from ſeeking of Aſſes, and his ſecond from following the Sheepe great with young: to ſet vp pictures in Galeries, and the names of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melies in a long row, with Coates, and Creſts.</hi> Notos magis facit quam nobiles, <hi>doth giue knowledge of men, but no honour vnto them: the flower and the branne comes both out of the ſame roote: and euery man in himſelfe is but as a figure of</hi> 1. <hi>giue him riches there is a</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12979:6"/> 
               <hi>cipher</hi> 0. <hi>then may he ſtand for tenne: giue him riches and authority, there be two ciphers</hi> 00. <hi>then may he ſtand for a hundred: adde ſauour of his Prince, there is a third cipher</hi> 0 <hi>then may he ſtand for a thouſand: Thus euery man in himſelfe is but as a figure of</hi> 1: <hi>diſtinguiſhed only by empty ciphers.</hi> No more for ſhame. Me thinks I heare either the prophecy of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay fulfilled in his third Chapter and 5. verſe, <hi>That the vile ſhould preſume againſt the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi> Or elſe as Eſdras ſpeaketh in his firſt booke and 3. Chapter, <hi>that they be the words of men in wine, who neither remember their King, nor their Gouernours.</hi> Did but <hi>reaſon</hi> inſtruct, or
<hi>common experience</hi> rule theſe ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, they would abhorre their tongues as blabbs of their owne baſeneſſe. In <hi>mettals</hi> of the ſame kinde (which <hi>Plato</hi> reſembleth vnto the ſoules of men) ſome are found to be purer then others. In <hi>Plants</hi> there is a great difference of ſeeds and branches. In <hi>Cattaile</hi> there appeareth no ſmall force of the breede. So is it amongſt <hi>Men</hi> (for in theſe things we are like to other creatures) it auayleth much from what ſtock one deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth. I confeſſe that
<hi>Aurelius</hi> was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie vnto Roome in nothing, <hi>ſed quiage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12979:7"/> but in <hi>Commodus</hi> his incommodious ſonne. That amongſt the Kings of
<hi>Iuda</hi> for the moſt part good Fathers had bad Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: <hi>Ne virtus videretur eſſe haereditaria,</hi> that vertue might not ſeeme to come by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance. And bad Fathers begat good: <hi>Ne vitium eſſet infinitum,</hi> leaſt vices ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede aboue meaſure. Yet for all this <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly</hi> it commeth to paſſe, that inclinations of minds do follow the originals and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of bodyes: and the Poet <hi>Horace</hi> ſayth truly, <hi>Eſt in iuuencis, eſt in equis patrum vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus &amp;c. Fortes creantur fortibus &amp; bonis.</hi> As the matter is affected whereof we are moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſo groweth there (<hi>euen in nature</hi>) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and diſtinct differences betwixt vs: ſome are noble, ſome ignoble, ſome ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſome baſe: ſome quick of apprehenſion, ſome dull: ſome fit to rule, ſome to ſerue. Neither is this repugnant vnto the lawe of <hi>Nature</hi> who although ſhe hath made thoſe things which are <hi>Neceſſary; common</hi> to all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet out of the <hi>variety</hi> of thoſe which receiue them, cauſed by <hi>Priuate</hi> beginning, and <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionate</hi> matter, doth there ariſe diuerſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of <hi>Singulers</hi> and many fold diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and affections of men. If children of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:12979:7"/> times, carry the markes of their fathers, grandfathers, great grandfathers, in there bodies: may we not iudge, that they retaine in there minds, the propenſions, inclinations, and as it were the ſparkes of there aunceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors? Which if it <hi>ſometimes</hi> hapneth other wiſe, yet in a dubble reſpect that matters not: firſt, Becauſe <hi>that</hi> is to bee conſidered, which commeth to paſſe <hi>often,</hi> not which ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom chaunceth;
<hi>Nature</hi> being wont, for the <hi>Moſt part</hi> to obſerue her lawes. Secondly becauſe it muſt be graunted, that education, diſcipline, and vſage, are very forcible, to the informing of manners, and confirming of habits: which we doe not ſay, doe of
<hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> follow the bodies temperature: and yet againe it may not be denied, but that the pure naturalls in ſome, are better then in others, for the procreation of morall, or ciuil vertues the region where we liue: our behauiour in our youth or kinds of life; of diet: of affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of minds, and differences of ſuch like thinges produce a variety of <hi>Next</hi> cauſes: and then a concluſion in <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> is this; That from hence muſt ariſe, a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of effects. It is not <hi>Reaſon</hi> nor
<hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> alone which pleades. In this cauſe <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12979:8"/> comming to his farme and ſeeing his houſe which he had builded, decayed, a tree which he had planted, rotten: a boy which hee had brought vp, now with a gray head: ſaith thus to him ſelfe. <hi>Quocunque oculos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verto, video documenta meae etatis.</hi> I find do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments of my age on euery ſide, To like effect may I ſpeake in this caſe of nobility<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <hi>Quocunque oculos conuerto video argumenta verae nobilitatis. Reaſon</hi> inſtructeth,
<hi>Experience</hi> teacheth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> behold I am coo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed with a cloud of honorable wittneſſes. <hi>King, Prince, Nobles</hi> are preſent; beſids all theſe, <hi>Diuine writ</hi> doth warrant the ſame. In the ſixt of <hi>Ezech.</hi> and the third verſe <hi>GOD ſpeaketh to mountaines hills, rockes,</hi> and <hi>vallies,</hi> and vnder theſe, to<note place="margin">for Riuers <hi>Hier<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> reads Rocks.</note> men of diuerſe ranckes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to <hi>vallies,</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people: <hi>Tor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ks:</hi> to ſoldiers, To <hi>hills,</hi> to gentlemen, <hi>To mountaines,</hi> to nobles. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> poſterity were of two ſorts, <hi>I will mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply thee as the duſt of the earth.</hi> Here is an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and a duſty generation. <hi>I will make thy ſeed as the ſtarrs of heauen,</hi> here be true <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> like ſtarrs, ſhining, and growing light vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world. Theſe in the firſt of <hi>Num.</hi> and the ſixteene, are called <hi>the famous in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in the ſecond of <hi>Samuel</hi> the 23. and
<pb facs="tcp:12979:8"/> 23. verſe <hi>the worthyes of the land,</hi> in the. 5. of<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eſay</hi> and 13. <hi>the glory of the Kingdome:</hi> in the
<hi>Epiſt</hi> of <hi>Iude</hi> the 8. verſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Dignity, Glories,</hi> or
<hi>Maieſties</hi> in the 26. of Ezek. and 11. verſe. <hi>The ſtrength of Iſrael.</hi> Hath God giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe names to things which haue no being? it was one of the high degrees of miſery in <hi>Iudaths captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to haue her Nobles ſlaine: Ieremy</hi> the 39. And <hi>Paule</hi> in the 1. to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the 1. and 26. ſpeaking of bad ones, tells vs heauy newes,
<hi>That not many Nobles are called;</hi> here are <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> but not <hi>many called.</hi> To hold any longer a Taper to the Sunne, were but a poynt of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: my text is cleare: <hi>Theſe were Noble men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be differences or degrees of Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. <hi>Theſe were (More) noble men, then thoſe of Theſſalonica</hi> The Kinds of nobility are foure:<note place="margin">I aſcribe nothing to Fortune though I will vſe the word.</note> One is by <hi>nature,</hi> an other by <hi>riches</hi> or (as we ſay), of fortune, a third <hi>Morall,</hi> a fourth <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> firſt, that by
<hi>Nature</hi> is by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his politiques thus defined.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Est virtus Generis, et alicuius familiae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruens quedam facultas procreandi viros inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuos, et ad vertutem faciles, ſuceſſione confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata.</hi> It is a power incident vnto a ſtocke, or a certayne congruent ability, of a houſe or famely, to beget an ingenuous progeny, apt
<pb facs="tcp:12979:9"/> to imbrace honorable vertues, and confirmed by ſucceſſion. This <hi>Kind</hi> then, is not ſo much in one <hi>indiuidual</hi> to be conſidered, as in a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued race</hi> or <hi>line of many;</hi> and ſuch is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, as that it may, and is many times, retayned without the other <hi>three,</hi> it is not impoſſible to bee <hi>Noble by birth,</hi> and thereby procliveto honeſt, and honorable deſignes, and yet bad education, to fall to vice, and thereby become voyd of <hi>Morall and deuine nebility:</hi> yea and ſome times of that alſo which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by <hi>Fortune.</hi> Such as be vicious ſtaine the noblenes of their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet doe they not altogether extinguiſh there <hi>Nobility,</hi> becauſe being noble by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſtill</hi> they retaine a power, to beget others which are procline to morall honeſty. For as <hi>Laban</hi> will either be a <hi>Laban,</hi> or a <hi>Nabal,</hi> or
<hi>Nabal</hi> either a <hi>Nabal,</hi> or a <hi>Laban,</hi> turne them backwards, and forwards they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine rude ruſtickes, ether a fooliſh clowne, as <hi>Nabal,</hi> or a frowning clowne, as <hi>Laban,</hi> for <hi>Mercury</hi> cannot be carued out of euery blocke. So is it with
<hi>Nobility</hi> by <hi>birth,</hi> it will not ſoone degenerate: as one man cannot well be ſayd to get it vnto his ſtocke, ſo bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once gotten, it cannot be ouerthrowne
<pb facs="tcp:12979:9"/> or loſt, by the wicked life of one. Now as on the one ſide, <hi>Vice</hi> doth greatly blemiſh it, ſo on the other, <hi>Vertue</hi> in a <hi>Noble</hi> perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage by
<hi>nature</hi> is farre more excellent and worthier eſtimation, then in a man by birth
<hi>ignoble:</hi> for in him, it is more firme, and conſtant, more deepely rooted, and as it were wreathed, and ſtrengthened with the virtues of his Aunceſtors, ſo as by a kind of neceſſity, he is conſtrayned to tread in their ſteps: yet in <hi>this,</hi> is virtue more admirable, more properly his, and formed in him with greater difficultie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond kind is an externall ſhape of <hi>Nobility,</hi> ſhining in
<hi>the goods of Fortune,</hi> which doth dazle and deceiue the eyes of common men: whence it was that <hi>Simoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> accounted thoſe to be <hi>Noble,</hi> which were deſcended in a long courſe of time, from wealthy Progenitors. This is not oppoſite vnto vice, as the trueſt Nobility is, for <hi>diuites in arca,</hi> may be <hi>pauperes in conſeientia,</hi> rich men in cofers, poore men in conſcience: and though <hi>Diues ſeculi,</hi> was <hi>Diſcipulus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, Ioſcph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> a diſciple of Chriſt, yet corpulent birds cannot flye high. Hee that is ſuperfluouſly rich, <hi>currit ad libitum,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12979:10"/> 
               <hi>&amp; corruit ad illicitum,</hi> ſayth <hi>Bernard:</hi> wealth and wickednes, are ſeldome while at oddes, whereupon it was not ſayd amiſſe, That the riches of
<hi>Midas</hi> were not more noble, then the pouerty of <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> and yet are riches alſo reckoned a part of Nobility. Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they make it popular. Secondly, for that they be the inſtruments by which ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are, or may be attayned. Laſtly, becauſe (beeing attayned) they likewiſe ſerue as meanes whereby thoſe vertues by actions do manifeſt themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third kind is <hi>morall,</hi> which is nothing elſe but a compoſition of manners confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the habits of vertues, which alſo may be called the <hi>nobility of the mind.</hi> This dependeth on our owne induſtry and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, being moſt propper vnto thoſe which haue it, becauſe they be the firſt founders or authors of the ſame: and it is not ſo ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to that <hi>by birth,</hi> but that it may be ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated. In the eight Chapter of
<hi>Iohn,</hi> Chriſt calleth the wicked Iewes the ſonnes of the Deuill, there was in them then no <hi>morall</hi> noblenes, and yet by <hi>nature</hi> were they deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended from honorable
<hi>Abraham:</hi> the worſt of them could ſay, we haue <hi>Abraham</hi> to our father. With this kind haue there been ſome
<pb facs="tcp:12979:10"/> ſo farre in loue, as that more out of affection then iudgement, they haue pronounced, <hi>Nobilitas ſola eſt animum quae moribus ornat,</hi> that the <hi>Morall</hi> is the <hi>Totall;</hi> the <hi>Soule,</hi> the <hi>Sole</hi> Nobility. I know it little benefits a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to come from a cleare Spring, if it ſelfe be muddy, that <hi>Eſops</hi> Iay did boaſt of other birds feathers; that it ſmally profiteth a blind man to ſay that his Parents could ſee; or a feeble man, that his Aunceſtors did wraſtle for the Garland in <hi>Olympus.</hi> Such as couet to excell in Honour, muſt labour to exceed in Vertue. <hi>Magna haec eſt,</hi> great ſurely is this kind, <hi>ſed non ſola,</hi> but not the onely kinde; in the opinion of many like <hi>Abiſhai</hi> amongſt <hi>Dauids</hi> Worthies, who had the name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<hi>three,</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Samuel</hi> the 23. Chapter, and let it (<hi>for me</hi>) beare the bell amongſt the <hi>former,</hi> yet muſt it yeeld to the fourth, which is the laſt:
<hi>Diuine or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Nobleneſſe,</hi> in compariſon of this, that other is at the
<hi>moſt,</hi> but as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to <hi>l'harao,</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> in the kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Diuine Nobility:</hi> It is an eleuation of our degree, or nature vnto GOD, a comming vnto him, a conformity with him: the top of this kindred is GOD himſelfe, and then
<pb facs="tcp:12979:11"/> doth it moſt appeare in vs, when neglecting mortall things we aſpire vnto heauenly, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating herein our holy predeceſſors the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and ſoules of the righteous, ſtriuing to liue as they do, fearing to degenerate from them, and euer remembring with <hi>S. Paul Philippians</hi> the 3. Chapter, and 20. verſe, that our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>our conuerſation be in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are then (you ſee) foure kinds of Nobility, firſt, <hi>externall</hi> by riches, ſecondly, <hi>internall</hi> by vertue, thirdly, <hi>naturall</hi> by birth, fourthly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> by grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Externall, or purſe Nobility,</hi> though it glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth in the face of the world, yet is it but ſeated in the hands of Fortune, <hi>quae vitrea eſt</hi> ſayth <hi>Seneca,</hi> a very brittle <hi>Shee</hi>-friend, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon an vnconſtant wheele, and pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Poets with a double face, <hi>white</hi> before, but <hi>black</hi> behind: her riches are run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagates (<hi>vncertaine</hi>) ſayth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the firſt to <hi>Timothie</hi> the ſixt Chapter, and 17. verſe, like euill Seruants, who loue often to ſhift their Maſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> that could ſay <hi>Dominus dedit, the LORD hath giuen,</hi> in the ſame verſe alſo ſayd, <hi>Dominus abstu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit, the LORD hath taken away.</hi> The whole world is alwayes in motion, and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:12979:11"/> in change; the heauen hath not one face long; the earth hath foure coates in the yeare, and the eſtates of the richeſt are very ſickle; as a blaſing ſtarre, to night apearing, to morrow gonne; as an Actor on the ſtage, ſometimes a great perſonage, ſometimes a poore peſant: as ſwans neaſts in the water: <hi>errantes inſule,</hi> wandering Iſlands: yea the mighty potentats of the world are but <hi>Ludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria fortunae, Fortunes</hi> ſcorne. <hi>Haman</hi> to day highly honored in the Court at <hi>Shuſhan,</hi> the next day hanged vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as high a gibbet: <hi>Geliner</hi> a puiſſant Prince of the <hi>Vandalls,</hi> but brought ſo low within a while, as he was inforced to requeſt a loafe of bread, to ſlake his hunger; a<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Procopius.</hi>
               </note> ſponge to drye vp his teares, and a harpe, to ſolace him in his exceeding miſery. <hi>Belliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> in his time the only man liuing, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his eyes put out, he was at laſt led in a ſtring to begg; crying: <hi>Date obolum Belli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſario. Henry</hi> the fourth a ritch and victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Emperour who had fought 52. pitched feilds, yet in his old age driuen to that exigent, as he became a ſuter for a poore prebend in the church of <hi>Spire,</hi> to maintaine him-ſelfe. Thus do men totter as it were vpon the ridge of a waue, and are turned (as we ſay) vpon
<pb facs="tcp:12979:12"/> 
               <hi>Fortunes</hi> wheele. And therefore ſuch as <hi>onely</hi> ſtrive thus to
<hi>Ennoble</hi> them-ſelues, doe fitly reſemble thoſe <hi>Arcadians &amp; Romans;</hi> who (as <hi>Phutarch</hi> ſaieth did weare the <hi>Picture of the Moone</hi> vpon there ſhooes, to tell them that as there <hi>Nobility</hi> did increaſe, ſo would it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe againe, and ſoone be ecclipſed. <hi>Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity internall;</hi> (ſo much applauded; as if
<hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes</hi> were nothing els, but a famely beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, with the beſt vertues,) is but a habite, got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by vſe, powerfull (<hi>in ſome meaſure</hi>) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme morall actions:
<hi>ſtudy, care, diligence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bona
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>irps bona propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>right, conſultation, fit pre-election,</hi> are the beſt fountaines from whence it doeth ſpring, the beauty of it, conſiſteth in <hi>Action,</hi> and the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of it is but <hi>out ward Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nobility by birth,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> called it, hath but a weake foundation; the <hi>temperature</hi> &amp; <hi>right conſtitution</hi> of
<hi>Mortal</hi> bodyes, whereby <hi>Some</hi> menne are made <hi>Onely procliue,</hi> to honorable actions; and haue a facullty to procreate others, with <hi>ſparkes</hi> of honour, like to them-ſelues: And ſuch are the ruins of time, as there remaynes not ſo much as foote-ſtepps of many aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent famelies: (To omit hom-bread exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.) The <hi>Iulij, Fabij, Metelli,</hi> are ſo buried;
<pb facs="tcp:12979:12"/> as he that now ſhould but ſay hee deſcended of them: would be mockt and hooted at, as if he had told a dreame of <hi>Pythagoras.</hi> Onely <hi>Chriſtian Nobility</hi> is beſt which admits of noe exception: in regarde whereof all the reſt are but
<hi>ſhadowes,</hi> and <hi>ſhapes</hi> of noblenes: for in CHRIST IESVS ſaith Saint Paule
<hi>Gala.</hi> the ſixt and fifteene (<hi>nether circumciſion availeth any thing, nor vncircumciſion; but a new creature</hi> (Not <hi>Circumciſion</hi>) not the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of the lewe; <hi>which was much euery way Rom.</hi> the third and firſt, <hi>for to them apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the adoption</hi> and <hi>the glory</hi> and <hi>the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and the giuing of the lawe, and the ſeruice of GOD, and the promiſes: Rom.</hi> the ninth and fourth verſe. Not
<hi>Vncircumciſion,</hi> not the honour of the Gentiles, with, al their wealth, wiſdome, pollicies, pedegrees, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuer is of high account, and glorious in the eyes of the world. All priuiledges, all prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues, all dignities, all regalities; they muſt ſtoope, and lie downe, at the feete of a <hi>new creature. Paul</hi> (whileſt he was a <hi>Iewe:</hi>) was a citizen of <hi>Rome,</hi> a <hi>Phariſy,</hi> a great <hi>Rabby,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed at the feete of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Beniamine,</hi> circumciſed the eight daye: after his conuerſion, (being a chriſtian) he
<pb facs="tcp:12979:13"/> was an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> taken vp into the third heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. yet all theſe things, did he thinke, but as loſſe, and doung in reſpect of his being <hi>a new creature</hi> in CHRIST IESVS. This indeed is the ornament of the bloud, the beſt part of Noblemens ſcutchions, the fineſt flower in their garlands, and be they of neuer ſo great an eſtate and want this they are but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> wretched and vile and miſerable,
<hi>Apoc.</hi> the 3. and ſeuenteene. To haue <hi>wiſdom, wealth, ſtrength, beauty,</hi> is in compariſon nothing: firſt <hi>Cor.</hi> the firſt: and 25. 26. 27. verſes. To be
<hi>King or Keſar:</hi> is in compariſon, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: <hi>for the King may not lift vp his mind, aboue his bretheren. Deutro:</hi> the 17. and 20. ver &amp; Caeſares <hi>eſſent Chriſtiani ſi</hi> Caeſares <hi>non eſſent ſecule neceſſarij aut ſi Chriſtiani potueſſint eſſe</hi> Cae ares, ſaith <hi>Turtulian</hi> of the <hi>Caeſars.</hi> To be the <hi>Mother</hi> or <hi>Brother</hi> of CHRIST, is in compariſon nothing, for if theſe had not been allyed vnto him by ſpirituall adoption, as wel as by naturall propagation, they could not haue been ſaued, <hi>Luke</hi> the 11. Chapter, and 27. verſe, and <hi>Marke</hi> the third Chapter, the 33. and 35. verſes. Only a <hi>new creature</hi> ſhall <hi>ſtand,</hi> when all things elſe ſhall <hi>faile,</hi> and then are we truly honorable, when our
<pb facs="tcp:12979:13"/> pedigree runneth vpwards with Chriſts (in the third of <hi>Luke</hi>) to this height, <hi>Which is the Sonne of Adam, which is the Sonne of God.</hi> I call not there a Chriſtian Noble: <hi>A new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> as if he lately came out of <hi>Affrica,</hi> or had neuer been heard of in the world before: for (as <hi>Bildad</hi> ſpeaketh in the 8. of
<hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>theſe are not men of yesterday:</hi> Though the name of <hi>Christian</hi> began firſt to be publiſhed at <hi>Antioch,</hi> yet before <hi>Chriſt was borne,</hi> was this broode honorable. Who can exclude <hi>Moſes</hi> from it, who preferred the reproch of Chriſt before the Court of <hi>Pharao?</hi> Or <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> who beheld Chriſt leaning on the top of the ladder, and did him reuerence? Or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> who ſaw the day of Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced exceedingly? Theſe (and many more) were all noble Chriſtians, indued with Chriſts ſpirit, and yeelding ſeruice vnto him, ſo that ſome went before, and ſome follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed after, but the ſong of all was one, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna in the higheſt.</hi> The worth and dignity of Chriſtian Nobility conſiſteth in this, that it maketh the <hi>Sonnes of men the Sonnes of God,</hi> not by the grace of <hi>Creation,</hi> as <hi>Adam</hi> was in his innocency, nor by the grace of <hi>perſonell vnion,</hi> as Chriſt is in his manhood,
<pb facs="tcp:12979:14"/> but by the <hi>gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce of adoption,</hi> whereby we cry Abba Father, the acts whereof is double, 1. <hi>acceptation,</hi> 2.
<hi>regeneration:</hi> by the <hi>former,</hi> we are <hi>all equall</hi> to thoſe which are the
<hi>beſt:</hi> by the <hi>latter,</hi> we are made not Sonnes <hi>more</hi> then others, but yet
<hi>better</hi> Sonnes of God And then are theſe <hi>Nobles borne,</hi> when the Sonne of righteouſnes ariſeth in their ſoules, enlightning their minds, and offering vnto their inward viewes the iudgements of God for ſinne, <hi>hic dolor eſt partus,</hi> this is the paine of their birth, <hi>haec veſpera eſt</hi> ſayth <hi>Barnard,</hi> this is the ſorrow of the euening, <hi>&amp; neceſſe eſt addimatutinam laetitiam,</hi> and for a full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance, the gladneſſe of the morning muſt be added, a ſweet excuſing ioy of conſcience, a
<hi>laetitia,</hi> that is a <hi>latitia,</hi> which maketh the heart farre more wider then the mouth, and thus is their <hi>birth conſummate,</hi> when <hi>evening</hi> and <hi>morning</hi> are made <hi>one day.</hi> As they haue a <hi>birth,</hi> ſo haue they alſo a <hi>growing:</hi> they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in yeares, and with yeares grow in fauour both with GOD, and Man, let
<hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> who was not only in high eſteeme amongſt the people,
<hi>ſed magnus coram Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino, Luke</hi> the firſt Chapter, but <hi>great like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the ſight of GOD,</hi> deriuing not onely
<pb facs="tcp:12979:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> their <hi>deſcent</hi> from the King of glory, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alſo this King their <hi>moſt louing Father,</hi> being all <hi>Kings ſonnes,</hi> and <hi>beloued of their Father,</hi> all <hi>Brothers to Chriſt,</hi> the firſt borne among many brethren, all
<hi>yonger brothers indeed,</hi> but (which is wonderfull) all <hi>Princes apparant, Reuelat,</hi> the fifth Chapter and the tenth verſe: and that to Crownes incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably preticus, both for their valew, for <hi>they are Crownes of life, Timoth.</hi> the 2. Chapter, and 4. verſe: and alſo for their glory, for <hi>they are incorruptible Crownes of glory, Peter</hi> the firſt, and 5. Chapter and 4. verſe. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing yet further the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> for their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable comforter; dwelling in them, ſpeaking to them, praying with them, and crying for them, with ſighes, and grones, which cannot be expreſſed: whoſe <hi>garments</hi> are the vnſtayned roabes of their Sauiours righteouſnes, whoſe <hi>Chayne,</hi> is the golden Chayne of their ſaluation, the links where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are deſcribed <hi>Rom.</hi> the 8. Chapter and 24. verſe: whoſe <hi>good cognoſcence</hi> is a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, whoſe <hi>ſignet</hi> is the ſpirit, pledging and ſealing vp their hearts to the aſſurance of life, whoſe <hi>Iewels and ornaments</hi> are the graces of that ſpirit, as ioy, peace, humility,
<pb facs="tcp:12979:15"/> faith, loue, hope, patience, &amp;c. whoſe <hi>diet,</hi> more choiſe then Manna, is that liuing bread which came downe from Heauen, whoſe <hi>vaſſals</hi> are all the creatures, and whoſe <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants</hi> are the Angels, pitching themſelues round about them,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. and verſe 7. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring vnto them: miniſtring vnto them for their good: for the good of their ſaluation, <hi>Hebr.</hi> the firſt Chapter and 14. verſe. Theſe be thoſe vnto whom GOD beareth an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall affection, whom he hath <hi>elected</hi> before the world, <hi>called</hi> out of the world, <hi>iuſtifyed</hi> in the world, and whom he will
<hi>glorifie</hi> in the world to come. Tell me now, is it not the greateſt honour to be a true
<hi>Chriſtian Noble?</hi> What ſhall be done vnto the <hi>man whom the King will honour?</hi> the queſtion is anſwered in the 6. Chapter of <hi>Heſter,</hi> Hee ſhall be arrayed with royall attire, with the Kings ring on his hand, his princely diademe ſet vpon his head, and withall a Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be publiſhed, <hi>The Viceroy in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> Heere be ſinguler aduancements, yet the <hi>higheſt</hi> of theſe is farre inferior to the
<hi>leaſt</hi> and <hi>loweſt,</hi> which GOD beſtoweth vpon <hi>true Chriſtian Nobles.</hi> Our honours, are of a higher ſtrayne, darkening the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties
<pb facs="tcp:12979:15"/> of the world, as the Sunne obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the light of leſſer Starres. It was a high ſtep of earthly honour to which <hi>Moſes</hi> was mounted, when he was called <hi>The Sonne of</hi> Pharaoes <hi>Daughter:</hi> doubtleſſe it is a great bleſſing of GOD, to bee borne of any honorable parents; the Sonne of GOD, though hee came poore into the world, yet would hee not deſcend of anignoble ſtocke, and <hi>Paul,</hi> in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> when hee would magnifie the dignity of CHRIST in both natures, ſaith of him, that he came of
<hi>The linage of</hi> Dauid, according to the fleſh. Nobility, it is in earth the image and ſplendor, of GODs diuinity. O what is then <hi>Chriſtian Noblenes?</hi> how matchleſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſſing is it, to be allyed vnto <hi>diuine nature?</hi> to call the <hi>high GOD of heauen,</hi> our father? was it ſuch an honour that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Sonne of
<hi>Saule a wicked King of Iſraell?</hi> and can it ſeeme a ſmale thing, to become the Sonnes, of the <hi>holy one,</hi> the <hi>GOD of Iſraell?</hi> O behold, what loue the father beareth vs, that we ſhould be called, not <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants</hi> any more but <hi>friends, Iohn</hi> the 15. and 15. verſe Nay more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of GOD not ſo much <hi>the Sonnes of Men, as the Sonnes of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12979:16"/> 
               <hi>GOD.</hi> It was not our birth day, when wee <hi>firſt ſam</hi> light, and were borne into the world but when GODS countenance did <hi>firſt</hi> ſhine vpon vs, when ſaluation in CHRIST IESVS, was offered vnto vs. The <hi>Graecian</hi> virgins reckoned their age, from their marriage, ſaith <hi>Homer,</hi> and then began Chriſtians to liue, when
<hi>first</hi> we are eſpouſed vnto our huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band CHRIST. Let other men therfore, ſhew the images of their <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> let them fetch their pedigree from <hi>Hercules,</hi> or if they thinke it ſo fit, let them deriue themſelues from <hi>lupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> ſo as we may haue this honour of the Saints, <hi>to call the immortall GOD our Father,</hi> ſo as we may ſay:
<hi>Our Father which art in heauen.</hi> Which we may boldly do, if we feele the power of the ſpirit within vs, if GOD hath anoynted vs with the oyle of gladnes aboue others, if wee haue our partes in <hi>Diuine Nobility.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Nobility hath and is knowne by fruits.</p>
               <p> 
                  <hi>They received the word readely, they ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ehed it dayly.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>I may not belong in meaſuring out of <hi>frutest</hi> to preſcribe in this poynte, were with doting <hi>Phormio,</hi> to entreat of warfare before Captaine <hi>Hamball,</hi> in generall therefore a
<pb facs="tcp:12979:16"/> word, or two for the finiſhing of my text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nobles,</hi> may not reſemble the <hi>Noblest trees</hi> ſuch as were conſecrated to the Heatheniſh Gods: for they for the moſt part, were <hi>either barren,</hi> or without
<hi>good fruit</hi> as the <hi>Oke,</hi> the <hi>Beech,</hi> the <hi>laurell,</hi> the
<hi>mirtle.</hi> They may not be like <hi>Beaſtes,</hi> wherof the <hi>Nobleſt,</hi> are the
<hi>crueleſt:</hi> nether are theſe the vertues of <hi>Noble men,</hi> to dice well, to drinke well, to waſte lauiſhly, to wanton it veneriouſly; to forget that they were euer borne, or that they ſhall euer die: ſay not wee haue <hi>Abraham</hi> to our father: ſtand not ſo much vpon the bloud you haue; as vpon the good you doe: <hi>fruites</hi> you muſt bring forth, &amp; <hi>good ones toe:</hi> euery tree that bringeth not forth <hi>good fruit,</hi> is hewen downe and caſt into the fire. Luke the 3. <hi>there is danger els vnto your ſelues: and the ſeed of the wicked ſhall not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned for euer. Eſay.</hi> the 14. and 20. verſe,
<hi>here is Daunger els vnto your progenie.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to whom much is giuen, much is of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> required, where the Lord ſoweth liberally, there he expecteth a plentifull crop; and the
<hi>better the frutes</hi> arc, the more they argue a <hi>true Nobility. Iuſtice, Wiſdom, bounty, Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence greatnes of mind,</hi> ſeene in iminent daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; <hi>fortitude, gentlenes</hi> &amp; <hi>clemency</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:12979:17"/> ſuch like; are <hi>good fruits common</hi> to all the <hi>kinds</hi> by which they are made profitable not to them-ſelues alone; but do ſhine as ſtars, &amp; are helpfull vnto others. And hence it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe that euen by inſtinct of nature, we doe willingly obey a generous and noble perſonage; this cauſed the ſheepheardes to yeeld obedience vnto
<hi>Romulus,</hi> though brought vp as a ſheepheard amongſt them: they beheld in him a noble ſpirit, &amp; notable vertues, directed not ſo much to <hi>priuat</hi> as to <hi>publike</hi> good. There is a queſtion moued by<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Piccolo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus.</hi>
               </note> a Philoſopher of our age, concerning men, being <hi>noble by Nature, and quality of mind,</hi> yet oppreſied with
<hi>pouerry,</hi> and hauing the world to frowne vpon them, what calling they may chooſe, and life profeſſe wherein they may be <hi>fruitefull?</hi> His anſwere is good, that in noe caſe they may practiſe any baſe, or mechanicall trade, wherein men of low degree may be imployed with prayſe, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation; but either (ſaith he) they muſt addict them-ſelues vnto atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Prince, in ſome honorable office: <hi>for the pleaſure of a king,</hi> is (not a wealthie) <hi>but in a wiſe ſeruant, Pro.</hi> the 14. and 35. or they may giue them-ſelues vnto Chevalry, and leade a martiall life: for it is a peece of happines to
<pb facs="tcp:12979:17"/> a country, (if there can be happines in war) when as Captaines are gentlemen, and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen Captaines, or laſtly they may bee <hi>Prieſts.</hi> I wot well, that this ſort of people, for the ſpace of many yeares, haue had little honour by Parliament giuen vnto them: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſtanding by a rogue whilſt he is whipt, and keeping a beggars regeſter may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led honour. Yet to be a <hi>Mayor</hi> of a Towne or Citty, or a <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of Peace in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey (I might goe higher) cannot ſort ſo well with noble eſtate, as
<hi>Prieſthood</hi> may: heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in may <hi>Nobles</hi> liue, and deuote them-ſelues vnto Gods ſeruice without diſparidgement. The Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> was a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> a man of God, an <hi>honorable man,</hi> ſayth the text the firſt of <hi>Samuel</hi> and the 9. Chapter. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarks were <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> in their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, <hi>Vos genus electum, regale Sacerdotium,</hi> Ye are a choſen generation, a <hi>royall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> the firſt of <hi>Peter</hi> the ſecond Chapter and 9. verſe. <hi>Ecce cum regia dignitate Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotium</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hieron.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>copulauit, Prieſthood</hi> is ioyned with <hi>regalitie. Rex non eſt merè laicus,</hi> a
<hi>King</hi> may be a <hi>Prieſt</hi> without diſhonour. Many of your Aunceſtors (<hi>Right Honorable</hi>) haue liued in this <hi>order,</hi> and thereby not onely <hi>retained</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12979:18"/> their noblenes, but <hi>amplified</hi> alſo, and <hi>enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> the ſame: which craueth <hi>vnto vs</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance ſtill of a good regard at your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours hands. What kind of men may better entertaine the word of God, then the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the word? Who vſe more diligently to ſearch the Scriptures, then Miniſters, the interpreters of the Scriptures, and yet are theſe the onely notes whereby the Apoſtle doth commend vnto vs heere the <hi>moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable</hi> men. The fruites then of the <hi>beſt Nobles</hi> are theſe, with <hi>readyneſſe to receiue the word: with dilligence to ſearch it.</hi> Two
<hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> to <hi>Receiue:</hi> to <hi>Search.</hi> Two <hi>conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: readily: dayly:</hi> the obiect of both, <hi>the word of GOD,</hi> the end of both, <hi>to be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the truth. Zegedine</hi> tells vs of foure fruites whereby true Chriſtian Nobles may bee diſcerned. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> they acknowledge CHRIST to be their Sauiour.
<hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly,</hi> they are indued with his ſpirit. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre to ſerue ſinne. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> they are ſtrong in faith, all which are couched in the words of my text: for he that <hi>receiueth the word,</hi> muſt needs acknowledge CHRIST; he that <hi>receiueth it with all readineſſe,</hi> hath aſſuredly his ſpirit: <hi>he that ſearcheth the Scriptures day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12979:18"/> attendeth not vnto ſinne: <hi>he that ſearcheth</hi> (with theſe Baereans)
<hi>to confirme himſelfe,</hi> groweth from faith to faith, from ſtrength, to ſtrength, till he commeth to be a perfect man in Chriſt Ieſus. To <hi>receiue the word,</hi> doth not barely ſignifie, to <hi>take it,</hi> but to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, Actes</hi> the 3. Chapter and 21. verſe, and like good ground <hi>to fructifie, Mark</hi> the the 4. Chapter. <hi>To ſearch,</hi> is not an <hi>idle,</hi> but an <hi>earneſt inquiry:</hi> to <hi>ſearch with lights, Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phany</hi> the firſt Chapter, <hi>to looke into hearts and reynes, Pſal</hi> the 7. into euery cranny and corner, very narrowly. <hi>To receiue readily,</hi> argues a <hi>willing minde;</hi> to
<hi>ſearch dayly,</hi> an <hi>induſtrious ſpirit:</hi> to <hi>ſearch for to learne,</hi> an
<hi>humble, and an honeſt heart.</hi> The ſumme of all then, is this, The <hi>beſt Nobles</hi> makes <hi>beſt account</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell of Chriſt:</hi> they heare it with a glad heart, they ſtudy it, to amend their lines by it; they ſay vnto it, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid vnto <hi>Elias,</hi> I will not forſake thee, and with noble <hi>Ioſua,</hi> they meditate in it, day, and night. Let your Lordſhips therefore bee pleaſed to giue me leaue (as
<hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh in his ſecond Epiſtle and third Chapter) to <hi>ſtirre up, and warme your pure mindes,</hi> and though you haue knowledge, yet to put you
<pb facs="tcp:12979:19"/> in remembrance of theſe dutyes. If you care to be in the number of thoſe who are
<hi>the beſt:</hi> If you tender the continuance of that Honour which the Lord hath already pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon you; or expect any future acceſſe thereunto (as <hi>Hierome</hi> ſayd to
<hi>Salu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na</hi>) <hi>Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in manibus ſit diuina lectio, Let the word of GOD dwell in you aboundantly.</hi> Perſiſt in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noring the higheſt <hi>with your hearts,</hi> by giuing glory vnto him <hi>with your liues,</hi> by adorning his doctrine <hi>with your countenance, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> by incouraging the practiſes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of pietie: and as when the Lyon roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, the beaſts of the Forreſts doe tremble and quake; ſo when the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda</hi> ſpeaketh (though but by a meane meſſenger) you that be of his Court yeeld him reuerence. Theſe be the paths beaten by the nobleſt Chriſtians: in theſe ſtandeth the whole duty of <hi>men moſt honorable:</hi> vpon performance whereof, and no condition els, the Sonne of GOD himſelfe made challenge to the glory of his Father, <hi>Iohn</hi> the 17. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and 3. verſe, <hi>I haue glorified thee on earth, and now glorifie me with thy ſelfe in heauen.</hi> Bleſſed be the <hi>GOD of glory,</hi> who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decked this Land with ſuch <hi>glorious lights,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12979:19"/> ſo many <hi>noble Christians:</hi> and if that <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom be happy, whoſe King is the ſonne of Nobles, Eccle.</hi> the 10. Chap. and 17. verſ. then aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly great is our happines: hauing <hi>in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of Nobles,</hi> ſo <hi>Noble a King,</hi> in all kinds of <hi>Nobility, Noble by nature:</hi> a King, not by ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but by birth, deſcended from a moſt ancient, and matchleſſe ſamely. <hi>Noble by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> hauing his lap filled with all her fauours: being owner of Kingdomes, Countries, and Cities, wealthy and populous, which adds a ſplendor, and Maieſty vnto him. <hi>Noble mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,</hi> poſſeſſed with heroicall vertues, and beawtifyed with a true Idea, of a princely minde. <hi>Diuinely Noble,</hi> the Defender of the true faith: who is the Sonne of <hi>Adam,</hi> who is the Sonne of GOD. <hi>Noble by an exact conſpiration of all kindes together.</hi> Whoſe <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and
<hi>immortali ſeed,</hi> is Nobilitie from Heauen: whoſe <hi>Materiall,</hi> is Nobility from Nature, whoſe <hi>immediate forme,</hi> is nobilitie of manners; whoſe <hi>inſtrumentall</hi> and <hi>externall fulgor,</hi> is nobility of Fortune. This is the moſt perfit, and moſt rare
<hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> in the world, ſhining in ſome fewe Chriſtian Princes and Nobles, from
<hi>GOD, Nature, Vertue, Fortune.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12979:20"/>
            <p>The Lord bleſſe your <hi>Royall Maieſty,</hi> that as you haue receiued the word from your youth, ſo you may defend the faith with conſtant reſolution, and loue the Goſpell vnto your liues end. The Lord bleſſe all your <hi>Nobles,</hi> that as they be by their beſt title, (<hi>Christian</hi>) ſo their <hi>fruites</hi> may be euer anſwerable to their calling. The Lord bleſſe the <hi>worthy Prince,</hi> with the reſt of the <hi>young</hi> and <hi>Honorable Branches</hi> of this Land: and make them know, that if <hi>Angels</hi> fall, they become
<hi>Princes</hi> of darkenes; that if <hi>young Nobles</hi> degenerate, they become the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon calamities</hi> of their Countrey; that they are as ſo many <hi>Lucifers</hi> fallen from Heauen. The Lord for his mercies ſake bleſſe <hi>vs all,</hi> that hauing GOD to our Father in this life, we may raigne with Father Sonne and Holy Ghoſt in the life to come. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12979:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
